<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Heraclitus, or, Meditations vpon the vanity &amp; misery of humane life first written in French by that excellent scholler &amp; admirable divine Peter Du Moulin minister of the sacred word in the Reformed Church of Paris ; and translated into English by R.S. gentleman.</title>
            <title>Heraclite. English. 1609</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2575</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24336512</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24336512</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20946)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1850:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Heraclitus, or, Meditations vpon the vanity &amp; misery of humane life first written in French by that excellent scholler &amp; admirable divine Peter Du Moulin minister of the sacred word in the Reformed Church of Paris ; and translated into English by R.S. gentleman.</title>
                  <title>Heraclite. English. 1609</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
                  <author>Stafford, Robert, 1588-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 121 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation attributed to Robert Stafford--Cf. STC (2nd ed.) and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E¹² F⁸.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 18 and 66 misnumbered 8 and 69 respectively.</note>
                  <note>STC 7325 on reel 1064 is actually STC 7325.5--Cf. reel guide.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27533:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27533:1"/>
            <p> HERACLITVS: OR MEDITATIONS VPON THE vanity &amp; miſery of humane life, firſt written in French by that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Scholler &amp; admirable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Peter Du Moulin</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the ſacred word in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church of Paris:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And tranſlated into Engliſh by</hi> R. S. Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at Oxford by Ioſeph Barnes.</hi> 1609.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:27533:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27533:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS MVCH HONORED FATHER: S. F. S.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The naturalre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, that an obſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſonne oweth to a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and carefull father, obligeth me to meditate on ſome thing that may deſerue your pervſall, and anſwere part of your expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation: hauing therefore taſted the fruites of many mens inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I could not finde any ſort ſo holeſome for a man of your
<pb facs="tcp:27533:3"/> yeares, nor ſo pleaſing to mine ovvne reliſh as this enſuing treatiſe of that worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and admirable divine <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Du Moulin,</hi> vvho by his tongue, and pen doth daily win many ſouls to God, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would by the ſubtill deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sathan, and the perſuaſiue diſcourſes of vvicked Maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſts, and ſin-plotting Ieſuits run headlong to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. I know your expence in my breeding may iuſtlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire as great a worke as this immediatly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſelfe, which I ſhoulde bee as willing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, as you to command, were it not that I looke backe into this age as ful of envious detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; idle cenſures, as voide
<pb facs="tcp:27533:3"/> of all true iudgement, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Moreover this matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a diuine morality, or rather a morall diuinity woulde ſeeme too graue for my youth, and too high for my knowledge. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am the rather deſirous to make vſe of this Tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will ſerue not only as a buckler againſt thoſe criticall ſhafts, which ſome muſty quiuer might ſend out againſt me, but alſo as a comfort &amp; reſtoratiue for your declining age. I haue preſumed to dedicate it to your fatherly cenſure, as being yet vnable to apprehend any other thing that may either adde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to it ſelfe, or deſervedlie attract any favor fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you: hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling craving that the errours
<pb facs="tcp:27533:4"/> of this Tranſlation may not any way impeach your good opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but as you haue formerly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo now &amp; ever after you will bind me to reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt obſervant and reſpectiue ſonne <hi>R. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27533:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE AVTHORS EPISTLE Dedicatory to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ANN</hi> of Rohan, Siſter to the Duke of Rohan.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This book which warreth againſt the vanitie of humane life, is deſeruedlie due vnto your Ladyſhip, who hath truly vanquiſhed it in your ſelfe. I encounter it with words, but you ouercome it by actions. And actions doe ſo far ſurpaſſe words, as health excelleth a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, and as victory is more honorable then a combat. Your name only in the beginning of
<pb facs="tcp:27533:5"/> my booke ſhall ſerue for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for if this little worke be a true portraiture of vices, your life is a perfect patterne of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite vertues. Alſo I doe inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly confeſſe to haue receiued from your perfections much aid toward the perfecting of this ſmall inuention. For to drawe out the Image of vices I am to repreſent the contrary of that which I do both ſee and admire in you; to haue the ſacred word of God often in your hand, but more often in your mouth: to be daily in prayer; to haue Modeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty without Art: to haue your hand open to the afflicted, and your eare deafe to vice: In vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding aboue your ſex, to haue humility below your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:
<pb facs="tcp:27533:5"/> to haue a firme and free zeale without any ſcruple, from which chriſtian prudency hath taken away al affected auſterity. Theſe are vertues that each a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part is ſufficient to attract ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, notwithſtanding they all concur in you. They are vertues that the greatneſſe of your houſe doth render more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, and the corruption of our age more admirable. An age in which vices are ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners, and wherein deboſching hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, and prophane vanity are paſſed into nature, and turned into complexion. In the midſt of theſe corruptions, you ſhine as a burning candle in an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure night. I am well aſſured that your modeſty permitteth
<pb facs="tcp:27533:6"/> not this diſcourſe; but the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like profit requireth it. To the end that each may knowe what eſtimation we haue of vertue. To the end alſo that thoſe vices which ſpread themſelues, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe amongſt vs, may be repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by your good Example, and that your vertues ſeruing as accuſations may be a meanes to incite vs to good. It is our glory that that ſacred ſeed which wee haue ſcattered abroad, hath fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into ſo fertill a land where it hath brought forth ſo rare fruit, eſpecially amongſt vs, who haue ſo many examples exſtant, that doe demonſtrat the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene true piety, and that ſuperſtitious deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which endeuoureth to obtaine the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="tcp:27533:6"/> of God by a ſeeming pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue action, which limiteth it ſelfe to a ſet number of reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted prayers, and hath reduced religion to the fingers ends.</p>
            <p>Hauing then had <hi>(Madam)</hi> ſo many reaſons to dedicate this writing vnto your Ladyſhip. This one being ſufficient, that I had neuer vndertaken it but by your command. For I am deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of thoſe orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that are required in this diſtaſtfull age: I haue not any great words, nor thoſe ſwelling tearmes that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fit frolike humors: I ſpèake not of the Barriquades of gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <note place="margin">The foole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in his ſermons before the K. of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> deſire, nor of the Eſcalades of vertues. I call not Ieſus Chriſt the Daulphin of heauen, neither doe I compoſe Orations vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:27533:7"/> Fanne and Noſegay, it ſufficeth me to write French, my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being only to be vnderſtood; and in deciphering of vices to plant in your ſpirit the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the loue of God. In meane tearmes I intend to diſcourſe of high matters, and with a coale to delineat out the truth. The defect that is in it ought to be imputed in part to my dulnes, in part to my condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is much buſied and diſturbed.</p>
            <p>It is hard for a man to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat amongſt the blowes of <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quebuſches,</hi> and to mount his ſpirit very high, when a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand oppoſed things doe tend downward and break his flight. But the ſelfe ſame ing enious
<pb facs="tcp:27533:7"/> diſpoſition, which ſolicited you to incite me to write, ſhall alſo cauſe you to ſupport the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of it. Becauſe (not think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the beginning, it ſhould haue paſſed forth of my houſe) it is not ſo well adorned as I could wiſh. But ſeeing that it muſt now trauerſe abroad by your commandement, my deſire is that it may be receiued as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hand of him, which prayeth to God for the proſperity of your moſt Noble family, which God hath honoured with his holy and diuine alliance, &amp; who hath noe other ambition the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to obey you, and remaine all his life</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips moſt humble and obedient ſervant, PETER du MOVLIN.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27533:8"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27533:8"/>
            <head>Meditations vpon the vanity and miſery of humane life.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning diverſitie of worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, doth cut our time into a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thouſand pieces. And every affaire doth take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs one part of our life, leauing vs no time, but that which wee gaine by theft; ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting ſome howers for to ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amine our ſelues in ſecret, &amp; to entertaine our mind with religious thoughts. Theſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary meditations haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in them to employ our wits. For the firſt ſubiect, which doth preſent it ſelfe to our pervſall, is <hi>a conſideration</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:27533:9"/> 
               <hi>of the vanity, and miſery of hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mane life;</hi> not for to moleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs any way, while wee are in it; but to prepare our ſelues to depart wel out of it. No man can aſpire as he ought to the future life, which doth not contemne this preſent Neither can any man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne this preſent, which doth not wel know it. And the way to truely know it, is to remoue it farre from vs, to withdraw it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our heart, and to baniſh it from our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. For worldly goods being neere at hand do both dazell the minde, and diſtract the iudgement.</p>
            <p>But let vs firſt enquire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee proceede, of ſome
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27533:9"/> one that hath paſſed this way. King <hi>Salomon</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Eccleſiaſtes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into that meditation, doth write, that <hi>vanitie is moſt vaine, all is vanity.</hi> That great &amp; mighty King, which had riches without exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, peace without trouble, glory without envy, who was obeyed of his ſubiectes, reſpected of his neighbours, and raigned fortie yeares, which was a ſufficient time to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent his minde, in ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous buildings, in multitude of horſes, in al varietie of ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies &amp; ſciences; who had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed his Spirit through all the ſecrets of nature, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Cedar,</hi> vnto the <hi>Hyſſope;</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:27533:10"/> Nevertheleſſe in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all, conſidering howe theſe ſweetes are confected with bitternes, how there is little co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie in theſe things, how there is ſmal content in all this travaile, he makes this the cloſe of all his actions, <hi>That all is vanity, and affliction</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. Cha. 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>of Spirit.</hi> But before that <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> had proved theſe things he learned that leſſon of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> his father, which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the 39. Pſalme, <hi>True <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> every ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is nothing but vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; hee wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth in a vaine ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, &amp; diſquieteth himſelfe in vaine, he heapeth vp riches, &amp; knoweth not who ſhall gather them.</hi> Let vs therefore accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rules of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb facs="tcp:27533:10"/> men, enter into that meditation, and taking that raſor out of their handes, make an <hi>Anatomie</hi> of our ſelues. There is no diſcourſe more ſerious the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which treateth of vanity. Nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation more high then to reaſon of our owne infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: ſeeing by that meanes man contemning himſelfe, is elevated aboue himſelfe. This vanity linked with miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, is to be conſidered, firſt in the <hi>Nature of man;</hi> ſecondly <hi>in his actions;</hi> &amp; thirdly <hi>in his thoughts and deſires.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The vanity of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man.</head>
               <p>FIrſt to ſpeake of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27533:11"/> originall; The moſt noble <note place="margin">The birth of Man.</note> of them, yea if he be the ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne of an Emperor, doth rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue his forme betweene the two baſeſt excreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Nature, &amp; there he is nouriſhed for time with the moſt impure bloud of all. He is there ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect to be bruiſed by the leaſt fall of his mother, or ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>d by the ſavour, which pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceeds from an extinguiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Lampe; his birth is ſhame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, in ſo much that wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> to bee publiquely ſeene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> childbed. It is alſo reputed an honour to kill a man, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore <hi>Duells</hi> adde to one much reputation; becauſe as it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhame for a man to be borne into this world; ſo it is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27533:11"/> to ſend him out of it. A manifeſt proofe that the life of man is evil, ſince that it is ſo great a diſhonor to beget it, and a greater glory to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it; ſeeing that alſo hee doth begin his life with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and beeing borne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable, tumbleth into his owne filth; whereas other living creatures, are no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner out of the wombe, but they fal on their feet, and are ready to goe, nor out of the ſhel, but they run for meate. He againe is borne vnto ſuch neceſſity, that he is compel'd to gaine his own liuing with the ſweat of his browes, whereas other liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe find all things rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27533:12"/> prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, man on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath need of habiliments: for hee which is the moſt noble in the world, is aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſhew his nakedneſſe, &amp; therefore hideth himſelfe vnder the ſpoiles of other Creatures. Hee is ſubiect to more maladies, then all the Beaſts together; to which the obſcureſt fogges or eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dew doe no hurt. They neuer bleed at the noſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they goe alwaies declining toward the earth; They are ignorant what the <hi>Catarre, Calcul,</hi> &amp; diuers ſorts of Agues, meane: Man only is capable to diſcerne theſe differences, and to feele their effects. For if there bee any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27533:12"/> beaſts which are more affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with diſeaſes, they are ſuch that liue limited within the precinct of ſome houſe, &amp; ſo receiue it by Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagion.</p>
               <p>But ſome will obiect, that man hath reaſon aboue the beaſtes, which is indeed the reaſon of his torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him to practiſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, &amp; pernitious deſignes: to be ſubtill in contentions, to winde himſelfe into other mens affaires, &amp; being once ſatisfied, to ſtirre vp an artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall appetite, and a deſire to drinke without thirſt. I am ignorant what the reaſon is, but we are much more ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ill then good, and that griefes doe more diſturb vs,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27533:13"/> then pleaſures can content vs. Scarce can we thinke of an abſolute health, but ſome torment or other doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly poſſeſſe vs, as the <hi>Tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach,</hi> or <hi>paine in the fingers end</hi> One drop of Gall will diſtaſt a whole veſſell of Sweetes: How much then of happy fortunes is required, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt one affliction?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The vanity of man in his Actions.</head>
               <p>MAn being borne ſo <note place="margin">Infancie.</note> poore, and baſe into this world, how many years ſteale from him before he re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue ability to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? How long, and labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is his inſtruction? What
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27533:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> time is conſumed, while hee trembleth vnder Maſters, for to gaine vnprofitable words and ſome little ſuperficiall knowledge? Alſo who doth not diſcerne in this part of his age, an vntoward perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, a contradicting hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and in one Infant ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, all the vices of man, as buddes, and graines of ſome future infelicity? The onely meane to appeaſe children, is to correct ſome one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. If any doe but touch one of their toyes, they overturne al the reſt for deſpite. The loue and reſpect which they giue to ther pop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pets are eminent ſeeds of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry. Such are the infants,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27533:14"/> that are begotten of the beſt of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: a graine of corne well vſed in growing produceth ſtraw, a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth an Infant vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed. Therfore you may know by the perverſity of your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the image of your cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
               <p>After mans infancy fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth <note place="margin">Youth.</note> his youth, which is an vnbridled humour; a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent heate, that provoketh him to vndertake things vnfit that leadeth him into al dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and that induceth him to reiect all inſtructions. O how many men doe wander in this way? How many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in this age are corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with too much pleaſure,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27533:14"/> lulling themſelues a ſleepe in the lap of ſuch, that ſeeke to ſtrangle them? O traitreſſe <hi>Dalilah,</hi> which ſeekeſt by thy inticing flatteries to deliuer vs to an enimy far worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> which is the Divell himſelfe! Such plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are like vnto guilded pils; which vnder their exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal beauty include bitternes. They are alſo like vnto freſh Rivers, that end their courſe in the ſea, looſing their ſweet reliſh in an Ocean of ſaltnes. True zeale cannot flouriſh vnder ſo nice and delicate a government; nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowledge of God, (which is a celeſtiall guift) be ſubiected to the belly, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27533:15"/> remaine amongſt ſwine that habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is only agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Divell; who b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the permiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus Chriſt hauing entred into a hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſwine, compelled them to runne headlong vnto thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> owne ruine, and who (as it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> recorded in the holy writ nouriſheth prodigall childr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with the huskes of pleaſure inſteed of their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>This heat being ſomwha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Ripe age.</note> allayed by age, and man no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come to his maturity, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hold other vanities, which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tend on him, although no altogether ſo viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſcho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching; yet more opiniona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, &amp; troubleſome. For the comes irremoueable care
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27533:15"/> domeſtique troubles, the knowledge of husbandry, contentions in law, and the labour of painefull Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nique Arts, all to the end, that he may gaine ſomwhat for his children, who ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him al that he hath it may bee, is onely requited with ingratitude, &amp; reproch. Theſe infelicities are the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, that man is alwaies wearied with the things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, deſiring onely things to come, &amp; continually endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to catch at ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ewhat that is already eſcaped; whereas if by chance they obtaine it, it diſſolveth to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as it is in their handes, or if they enioy it, it yeelds
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27533:16"/> no contentment, nor doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way appeaſe their fear, or ſatisfy their deſire. This evil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath many inconveniences.</p>
               <p>There are many men, <note place="margin">Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> which will hazard their life to win a little mony, that is to looſe their being, for to gaine the meanes to bee which miſſe the end, to ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine the acceſſories: As he which ſelleth his ſword to buy a ſheath: or his horſe to haue ſome provender: and to gaine worldly pelfe, not to ſerue his occaſions, but rather for himſelfe to ſerue it; to haue riches as one hath a feauer, which doth more often poſſeſſe the grieued then the grieued it. To bee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27533:16"/> like vnto a greedy dogge, which lying vpon hay, and not eating it himſelfe, will ſnarle when any other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neere vnto it. O miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable people, that liue poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to dy rich! that are moſt couetous in their declining age, which is to prouide for a tedious iourney, when it is euen finiſhed! But a man that feareth God, for to avoid ſo great an inconuenience, will conſider in himſelfe, what is the worth, and eſtimation of ſuch droſſe; and will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, that the Divell is the only giuer of theſe things, &amp; and ſeducer of mindes from true piety, and the diuine knowledge of the Almighty,
<pb facs="tcp:27533:17"/> who ſheweth vs what eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation wee ſhould haue of riches, in giuing largely to the wicked, within whoſe breaſts it doth fall, as a purſe into a ſtinking privie. Ieſus Chriſt doth giue vs an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, what repute is to be held of it, <hi>in committing his purſe to Iudas,</hi> when as he gaue his <hi>holy ſpirit</hi> to his <hi>faithfull A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</hi> And if he had thought wealth to haue bin the true felicity, no queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would haue gathered it more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly: but hee had not ſo much where to lay his head on. He hath willed vs to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour poverty by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And the great King of <note place="margin">Luk. 9.</note> the worlde will deſpiſe all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27533:17"/> things, that ſhall intice vs to affect the contrary. A little wealth will ſuffice vs to liue well, and leſſe to die happily: <hi>godlineſſe with contentment is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>a great gaine;</hi> wee are come naked into the world, &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhall wee goe out: peac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able pouerty is much better then troubleſome riches. But ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo fooliſh, that he had rather draw water out of a great diſturbed riuer, with difficulty and perill, then fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a little cleere brook with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility and eaſe; had rather take a great maſſe of gold vvith torment, and danger; then a little with peace and ſecurity; and in fine, hee will be nothing the more ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27533:18"/> Moreouer he ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that to bee loſt, vvhich was neuer gained by him: this kind of auarice is alwaies linked vvith enuie. If perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loſe his world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fortunes (according vnto that vvhich <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ſaith <hi>that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 23. 5</note> 
                  <hi>Riches taketh her to her wings)</hi> it doth ſomtimes diſtract hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſenſe, for to ranſake a couetous perſon, is to flea his skin fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his body, to take from him his riches, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue him of his heart, ſince that ſuch doe vvholy deuote both heart and affection to their vvealth. The faithfull conſidering theſe things, wil ſay vvith the wiſe man, that <hi>This is alſo a vanity &amp; afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:27533:18"/>
               <p> Like to this former vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <note place="margin">Ambition.</note> is that of thoſe, which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to honour, &amp; greatnes, with an extreame deſire. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt that multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which preſſe themſelues in mounting vp, thoſe that follow, endeuour to march vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, which go before: and at length three partes of them, being driven to ſtay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, ſwell with envy, and griefe at the reſt; when as thoſe that haue attained to the height of honour, drawe vp after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſcaling lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, fearing that otherwiſe, ſome by aſpiring might pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel their worth. But often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when they haue poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with theſe dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27533:19"/> they are like vnto <hi>Apes</hi> which having once climbed to the top of a tree, or houſe, doe ſit and make ill fauoured faces at paſſengers, &amp; retaine the people to gaze at their moppes: For then ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their weakneſſe doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and their vices growe emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; in ſo much that they finde more care, and feare in that ſtate of greatneſſe, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were moſt meane. The higheſt boughs are moſt ſhaken by the winde, and the points of ſteeples moſt bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſtormes, &amp; lightening. A man hath leaſt minde to ſleepe in beds of ſilke embro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with gold. The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt feare of poiſoning is at
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27533:19"/> Tables furniſhed with varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of delicate diſhes. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, it hath not beene heard, that any hath received hurt out of woode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cups. After an innocent tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, ſleepe ſeemeth pleaſing in a bed of ſtraw. <hi>This is alſo a vanity, and affliction of Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Aboue all that vanitie, <note place="margin">The life of Courtiers</note> which corruption doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually attend, there doth ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare in Princes Courtes a certaine noble captiuitie; where vnder the colour of greatnes, is the higheſt ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, &amp; thoſe gilded chaines, that fetter mens mindes. He which wil liue here, muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be maſked, &amp; prepared in one howre, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vert him
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27533:20"/> ſelfe into twentie ſeveral ſhapes, to entertaine manie ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, but no friends. There innocency is accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted meere ſimplicity, and to affirme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thing, is to diſproue the ſame. There are two ſorts of people in Court, which hate one the other, each knowing of it, notwithſtanding there is alwaies an emulation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, which ſhould firſt atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt any point of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to do the other ſervice; and bee the laſt that ſhoulde end it. But ſuch ridiculous complements, are like vnto Antike actions. Envy which doth ſupplant, and deceaue his neighbour, or that doth ſnarle in ſecret, is there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:27533:20"/> and to appeaſe it there is no way but by miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Vices &amp; degenerat actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are eſteemed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, as precepts, and part of their compoſition. Not to be corrupted by them, there requireth more faith then a graine of Muſtard ſeed. As Crowes builde their neſts in the higheſt boughes, ſo doth the Divel amongſt the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of men, where ſpreading his wings, hee clocketh for his little ones, which are his vices; becauſe there they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, more expoſed to the ſight, and never appeare but vvith authority. There alſo ſhall you ſee <hi>Cavalieroes,</hi> which out of their gallant
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27533:21"/> diſpoſition will kill one the other vpon the interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a word; a manifeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that their life is not much worth, which vvill ſell it ſo good cheape. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe kinde of men that are in ſuch occaſions ſo valiant, doe flie away, vvhen they ſhal ſuffer any thing fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods cauſe. Surely manie ſuch are required to make one good Martyr for the holy Goſpell. O how ill doe they vnderſtand the precepts of honour! <hi>This is alſo an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy life, &amp; extreame vanity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this alſo there is linked the vanity of another ſexe. <note place="margin">The vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> For the moſt part of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are vaine, not only out of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27533:21"/> weaknes, &amp; example: but alſo by expreſſe profeſſion. All their ſtudy is howe to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh vanity, and about this they haue great ſtrife, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For amongſt thoſe worldly luſters, you ſhall ſee women corrupted with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacies, ſubiecting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to faſhions, and aſpects of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, looſing the vſe of their feet, by pleaſing their fancie vvith too much neatnes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying the fourth part of their life, in attiring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: wearing haire bought out of <hi>Tyre-womens ſhoppes,</hi> painting their faces, Idolatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing their owne bodies, yet nevertheleſſe crucifying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a iuſt puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27533:22"/> of all things, yet ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſpeake vvell, viewing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in a looking glaſſe a thouſand times in a daie, &amp; calling conſultations vpon: particular haire. Poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who in altring the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of their haire, &amp; adding ſomwhat to their height, by extraordinary ſhooes, would diſprooue the ſaying o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, &amp; that he vnderſtood little, when he ſought to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie, <hi>that man could not mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 36. 6. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>one haire white or blacke, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> adde one cub it to his ſtature.</hi> Make but a collection of the time, that a curious woman doth ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d through al her life in dreſſing her ſelfe, and you ſhal finde, that it is more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:27533:22"/> a fourth parte of her age: This curioſity hath ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity vvith ſervitude. Who amongſt them will apply ſo much time in doing good works? And how commeth it to paſſe, that thoſe habits, which were giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to hide his ſin, are now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into ſin it ſelfe? What is the occaſion, that that vvhich God hath ordained to cover mans ſhame; ſerues novv to ſet forth his glorie? That that vvhich was an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of humility, is novv become the matter of pride? There is nothing ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the will, and glory of God, as that vaine vanity. For a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hindereth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:27533:23"/> the going of her owne feet, by wearing ſuch nice, and high pantoffles, hovv ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe fly avvay into a ſtrange cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for Gods cauſe? A fleſh that is ſo delicate, how can it endure to take reſt, being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for the teſtimonie of the divine Goſpel? A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which by reaſon of her painting cannot tolerate the heate of the Sunne, how can ſhee then endure the fire for the ſacred word of God? Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue our preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer afflictions, &amp; pervſe our appre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſhip to Martyrdome; and in the end you will find that <hi>Salomon</hi> hath not ſeene ſuch things in his time, and that <hi>The vanitie of vanitie,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:27533:23"/> vvhich he ſpeakes of, is infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to the <hi>vanity</hi> of this age.</p>
               <p>But novv behold another <note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> petti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fogging ſtrifes in law.</note> ſort of vanity, vvhich doth much vexe and trouble man. A roaring, crying, &amp; turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vanity, vvhich is armed vvith ſtings, &amp; couered with ſubtility: vvhich emploieth al the beſt part of mans life in petifogging ſtrifes, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the controverſies of importunate proceſſe. Doe but enter into ſome greate Hall, or place of pleading, you vvill admire at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed murmure, the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diſcipline, the weariſome courſes, and contentious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, &amp; vvill truly perceiue
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27533:24"/> that in carriage of all theſe things, there is no mention of God, vnleſſe perchance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvearing. And that there in the meane time, vvhile that two perſons doe conſume their eſtates, to gaine a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, commeth a third &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guileth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both of the prey, and oftentimes their charge in follovving, ſurmounts the principall. O hovv many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe liue by the loſſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? How many would faſt without riches, if all thoſe that endevour to conſume one the other, ſhould but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into familiarity &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? I doe thinke that God doth perceiue this confuſed &amp; murmuring multitude, in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27533:24"/> the ſame faſhion, as vve doe ſee a litle hillock ful of Ants, running togither pell mell, vvithout order, or reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>This is alſo a great vanity and affliction of Spirit.</head>
               <p>Some one it may bee knowing theſe things to bee true, vvill ſay neuertheleſſe, that there is in humane life ſome honeſt ſtudy, ſome lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable knowledge, and many ciuill, and religious vertues, vvhich cannot be compriſed vnder vanity, but deſerue to be much eſteemed. In this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion doth principally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the <hi>vanity of mans ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> for if the beſt of humane actions bee but vaine, how much more is vanity it ſelfe?
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27533:25"/> Let vs firſt begin to examine ſtudies and ſciences.</p>
               <p>In this our moderne time <note place="margin">Of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues</note> learning is onely reputed to be the knowledge of langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: &amp; thoſe that are learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, doe buſie themſelues to finde out hovv the Romiſh vvome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did ſpeake two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares ſince, how the ancient Romaines did appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel themſelues, how people did then affect Comedies, &amp; to refine ſome Lattine or Greeke words, that are now growne out of vſe by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. This kinde of courſe is to vſe a golden ſcepter for to take vp dong, to employ the vnderſtanding, which ought to flouriſh in one, to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27533:25"/> ſome baſe occupation, &amp; to make a feaſt of nothing, but ſauce. For the knowledge of theſe things is only profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſeaſon, no vvay good to nouriſh. Alſo there are ſome, that when they haue attained olde age, doe then ſearch for vvords, when they ſhould haue the things. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there are alſo, that begin to read grammar, vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are come to vſe ſpectacles. They learne rules to ſpeake eloquently in Latine, vvhen they are barbarous in their owne natiue language. So that their life is a continuall incongruitie. <note place="margin">Of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Phyloſophy and the ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces haue many thinges not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27533:26"/> only more high, but alſo har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der: like vnto pine aples in the higheſt parte of a pine tree, vvhich many ſeeking to obtaine, doe fall in climbing for them, vvhereas others doe breake their teeth that ſtriue to open them. Such is this learning, that as it indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man vvith much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; ſo alſo it addeth vnto him more care and trouble of minde. For <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, that <hi>hee which doth augment his knowledg, doth but increaſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 1. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>his ſorrow.</hi> Ignorance is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vvithout ſome commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in concluſion, when vve haue gotten all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of this knowledge, it extends it ſelfe not far, and is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27533:26"/> of ſmale vſe: For man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by all his Philoſophy at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a ſmall fly, or garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lettice, much leſſe of his owne compoſition. We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to trauerſe our ſpirits through all things, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers to our ſelues. We vvill knowe much, and performe little. To ſpeake more properly, our ſtudy is no labour, but rather an idle action, vvhich doth torment vs vvithout any hope of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement: Like vnto the Squirrells, that runne conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually vvithin turning Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, thinking to get avvay, vvhen as after al their paines taking, they ſtill remaine in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27533:27"/> the ſame place. We learne little vvith great paine, and that little doth ſcarcely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende our imperfections, but rather oftentimes addes more to them. One drop of wiſdome, guided by the feare of God, is more vvorth then all humane learning. For what doth it profit a Lawier in taking paines to gaine the proceſſe of another, if hee himſelfe be at variance with God? What commodity reapeth a Phyſitian, to iudge of another mans health, if he himſelfe be not as yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolu'd to feele the pulſe of his owne conſcience? What good is it to any, that haue learned the ancient hiſtories,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27533:27"/> if they be ignorant of thoſe things that paſſe in this time? Or to haue learned by Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy the motions, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of heauen, if they knowe not the meanes how to come thither?</p>
               <p>There be ſome, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake <note place="margin">Of Travai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers &amp; Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims.</note> long tedious voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, gaining many hoſtes, but few friends, promiſing to learne much in their iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as oftentimes they returne more fooliſh then thy went: and perchance ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing circuited the earth, doe ſorrowfully bequeath their body to it, for a concluſion to their perfected reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as flies when they haue paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many times round about
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27533:28"/> the candle, at length enter into the flame. After they haue ſeene ſo much land, there only requires a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for to couer them. With this vanity are they iuſtly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, which make long voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages toward ſome Saint, for to deſire that they may get children, when it may bee at their returne they finde that ſome officious neighbour hath diſcharged them of that care. <hi>This is alſo a vanity and affliction of Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perchance our ciuill ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues <note place="margin">Of Civill vertues.</note> haue ſome thinges that are of more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence. But here out of this alſo doth bud another vanity, ſeeing that thoſe vertues haue no
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27533:28"/> motion, but by vices. For choller giues an edge to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, Cowardice doth make a man to be more circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpect, and wary. Ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Auarice, &amp; Enuy, are as ſtings to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp; Induſtry. The feare of an ill report in many wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the cauſe of Chaſtity, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are ſober out of a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous humour, others for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity; friendſhips are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, either for the deſire of pleaſures, or for the hope of profit, the firſt being no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then a paltry bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery, nor the laſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe. Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe doth often ſerue for a cloake to ſuch couetous perſons: for many followe Chriſt <hi>in the</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:27533:29"/> 
                  <hi>deſert onlie to haue breade,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 6. 26.</note> which is to ſubiect their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to the belly, and the chiefe of vertues to the meaneſt of vices, but I knovv not which is worſe, either to fly away from Chriſt, or to follow him for gain: to ſerue him for mony, or to ſerue the Diuel for nothing. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it doth ſeeme moſt iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ignominious to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, either to leaue his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, or in following him, wrong fullie to make him a vallet to our concupiſcences. What can theſe vertues then bee that march vnder the Pay of the Deuill? <hi>Surely this is alſo a great vanity and manifeſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:27533:29"/>
               <p> Wherfore ſome (not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving anie thing in the worlde which is exempted out of this vanity, &amp; that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; impiety haue infected all ſorts of eſtates and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in humane life) doe thinke to wreſt themſelues out of it by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fining their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to ſome deſert, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning their minde to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual care, where being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all company they liue in continuall ſilence, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeaking but with God and themſelues. This ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie humour in manie doth proceede from a brutiſh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, in others from a weake ſpirite incapable of humane
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27533:30"/> ſociety, in others fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to be remarkeable for ſome extraordinary profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in others out of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content &amp; envy, that they are wearied in ſwimming againſt the current of this worldly ſtreame, and in having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all things ſtil contrary to their deſire; Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I do not doubt but that there be ſome which doe embrace this ſort of ſolitary life to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh themſelues from the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this world, &amp; to ſerue God with more liberty. But ſuch are much deceiued who willing to forſake the world do returne farther into it by other meanes, and are aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by worſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations. For
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:27533:30"/> then paſſionate griefes, curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, peeuiſh Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Hypochondriacall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, diſpaire, preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſelfe admiration doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly glide into me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſpirits vnder the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctity; all which do render the ſpirit diſconte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of an inſolent melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and preſumptuous devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth into madnes and want of ſence. A ſolitary man in the extremitie of his griefes and ſadnes hath no bodie to comfort him, &amp; comparing himſelfe with none other but himſelfe, hath this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, that he is ſome excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thing. But then luſtful deſires
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:27533:31"/> do doubly burne within him. For ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is of this nature that hee thinketh thoſe thinges moſt beautiful which are far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt remote from him. So Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> being in the <note place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome in his epiſtle to Euſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium.</note> midſt of a deſert, &amp; in his grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt abſtinency doth confeſſe that his minde was then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the dances &amp; Ballads of young maides, and that he did burne with incontinency and deſire. Beſides the Devill following Jeſus Chriſt in to the deſert doth plainelie ſhew that hee did iudge that place moſt convenient for temptation. Then if the Son of God was aſſailed by the Devil in the deſert, how ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth an Hermite or ſecluded
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:27533:31"/> perſon that can neuer be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted? Therefore the ſureſt way for a man is to ſeperate himſelfe from the world, not with his feet, but with his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, to expel it altogither from him, and his heart, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring otherwiſe that depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this world, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hee carrieth it with him. For as it is poſſible to be worldly &amp; vicious liuing far from the world: So is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to leaue the world with out flying into a deſert, &amp; to liue alone in the middeſt of company: To bee within a Court or Pallace ſpectator of vanity and troubles, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out participating of them: &amp; in the midſt of a babling mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:27533:32"/> to talke only with him ſelfe, and to entertaine his thoughts with God: And in the meane time to employ his endeauors to the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church, ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out his hand to the Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, for to reguide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the right way of Salvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, rather then to hide his Tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the earth, and to cut him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe cleane off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body, and all civill ſociety, as an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable member. So did the Apoſtles and thoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious lampes which haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned the Church of God, and which ſhine to this daie amongſt vs they being dead. I know wel that the opinion of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the beginning
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27533:32"/> of his Politiques is true, that <hi>He which is of a ſolitary di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is either of a moſt divine, or very baſe ſpirit:</hi> becauſe that hee doth eſtrange him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from all ſociety, either for that hee hath vertues more then humane, or that he is ſo contemptible and meane in reſpect of man, that he is vnworthy to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach neere him: But let him knowe which doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſolitarines, becauſe hee doth ſurpaſſe all men in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding or vertue, that he ought to repell that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and to condeſcend by humility and meekeneſſe to the imperfections of others, labouring for the good of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:27533:33"/> the Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale, either by worde or worke. For what are al thoſe perfections any more then ſhadowes &amp; obſcure traces, of thoſe perfections which are in Ieſus Chriſt? Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he tooke vpon him our ſhape and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongſt men, that there by he might ſaue them, and win ſoules to heauen. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conclude this point; Jf to fly from the world be a vanity, how much more to follow it? If vices and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments doe harbor in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, how much more in preſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and throngs of people? Truely if vanity bee in euery place, let vs ſay that <hi>All is tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:27533:33"/> 
                  <hi>and affliction of Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in the meane time that <note place="margin">Old age.</note> Man is buſied about all theſe vaine conceipts while hee is puſhing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime with his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, endevouring nothing al daies of his life but to riſe, &amp; to go to bed: to apparel him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp; to make himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: to fill his belly, &amp; to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuat his ſtomacke: Which is no more then a Circle of the ſelfe ſame importuning occupations: much like vnto a Millers horſe that alwaies treads one compaſſe: While hee is thus buſied with ſuch occaſions, beholde olde age ſtealingly arriveth, to which few do attaine, and all deſire. But if any doe peradventure
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27533:34"/> gaine that time, they deſire to haue it prolong'd to the vtmoſt. This age (being as grapes which haue loſt their iuice, and as the ſinke of mans life) is without que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the moſt vnhappy for thoſe men that are worldly: as on the contrary it is the moſt bleſſed for ſuch as are godly. For worldly men in this age are doubly poſſeſſed with waywardneſſe; their feare and diſtruſt doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; their iudgement wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth weake, and begins to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh: Wherefore wee doe wrongfully call a melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humour, wiſedome; or a diſability ſobriety, becauſe oldneſſe leaueth not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:27533:34"/> but pleaſure leaueth it. And therefore hee doth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſeruedly complaine that the time &amp; manners of men are cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into worſe, while nothing is changed but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. For in his youth all things pleaſed him, if they were neuer ſo bad; in his old age all things diſliked him, if they were neuer ſo good; Like vnto thoſe which being in a ſhippe thinke that the baukes moue, vvhen it is onely themſelues. It is alſo a vice incident to this age for to ſpeake much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are no more able to performe any thing; and that they think alſo the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues moſt fit to propoſe precepts
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27533:35"/> to youth, and to declare thinges of time long ſince. Like vnto a declining ſtate (as that of the Romaine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire) where there are manie talkers, but few valiant: &amp; not much differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from the aged time of the world, where are many curious diſputers, but few of the true religion. In this age alſo doth encreaſe the loue of wealth, &amp; earthly cares doe ſummon new for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt man; hee waxeth all gray, and every thing in him beginneth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to wither, onely his vices excepted. That ancient man of whom the Apoſtle maketh often mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being ready to dote, waxeth not olde in worldlie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:27533:35"/> age, but then is hee in his full vigour. He then fore-feareth approaching death, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his life like vnto an Eele which ſlideth away. In the meane time he determineth of tedious deſignes, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vp riches as if death ſtoode a far off, and durſt not appeare: The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man hath leaſt feare to die when nothing of worth remaineth in him, but the very leeſe &amp; dregs of life. Then doth hee prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe leaſt to gaine the future bliſſe, when age forwarnes him, &amp; every gray haire doth ordinarily advertiſe him: yea many times death takes for a gage one part or other of our body, as an arme, or eie,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:27533:36"/> or legge to ſerue for an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement that he will very ſhortly fetch the reſt. For old me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are affianced to the earth by a long vſe and habit: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they are vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to go to it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing remaineth in them but euill. <hi>This is alſo a vanity and great griefe of Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable &amp; weariſome tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, <note place="margin">Of death.</note> behold the approach of death, before they haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to liue, much leſſe to die. The moſt part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being taken out of this worlde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they know to what end they entred in. They vvoulde willingly prolong the date of their life, but death admits
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:27533:36"/> no compoſition: for it hath feet of vvool, but armes of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron: it commeth inſenſibly, but having taken once holde it never looſeth her prize. To this pace or ſtep man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſo ſlowly as poſſible he can: For if a ſhip ſhould ſinke amongſt the waues two hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred leagues from land, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding every paſſenger would ſtriue to ſwimme: not with an intent to ſaue his life, but to repell death for ſome minutes, and to render nature her laſt inevitable tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute. Every ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trembleth at this paſſage, and laboureth to ſettle himſelfe here. The ſole memorye of death, mournefull funerals, and the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:27533:37"/> reading of Inſcriptions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen on ſepulchres, doth make the very haire to ſtare and ſtand on end, and ſtrikes man with an horror and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it. Some repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent death terrible to the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect and deprived of fleſh, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conſider it with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion mixte with dread. Some particular man which not long ſince was clad in ſilke and ſhined vvith Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, is now aſſaulted with troupes of wormes, and breathes foorth intollerable ſents, while that his heire doth laugh in ſecret, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyeth the fruit of all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, which he himſelfe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enioyed. And never the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:27533:37"/> in this his very duſt and corruption doth appeare an ambition, and pride doth reſt it ſelf within his tombe. For then behold ſtately Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, ingraued ſtones that report ſome famous actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and proud titles vpon his tombe ſet out with falſe nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, to the end that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers by may ſay, Here ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a goodly ſtone &amp; a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted body, <hi>Surely this is a vanity of vanities, and one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame vanity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But all theſe are as Roſes <note place="margin">Of Hell.</note> in reſpect of the Thornes which follow: for the vanity and trauaile of this tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life is a happineſſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the torments of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:27533:38"/> death which doth ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the moſt part of men. It is a large way which leadeth to perdition, and few do find the way of ſaluation. Death commeth here to leuy ſouls for hell, and doth enroule great and ſmale, learned and ignorant; rich and poore; yea many which are eſteemed holy, and liue couered vnder the cloake of hypocriſy, to the end that they might goe to hell with the leſſe noiſe, and not be ſtaied by the way. This Hel is a place of flames, and yet there is perpetuall darkneſſe, where ſoules doe wax olde and yet neuer die; and where they liue conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to dy; where they
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:27533:38"/> burne without conſuming; where they mourne without compaſſion, are afflicted without repentance, where torment is without end, and paſt imagination. There the vnhappy rich man, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to giue poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> a crume of bread, doth now begge of him a drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, although whole riuers be not ſufficient to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh his heate. What if the Roddes that God doth pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Infants withall, doe ſometimes make them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt diſpaire, and euen curſe the day of their natiuity, as <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Ieremie</hi> did? What <note place="margin">Iob. 3. 1. &amp; 3. Iere. 15. 10</note> are thoſe afflictions that hee doth oppreſſe his aduerſarie
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:27533:39"/> withall? <hi>It is a horrible thing</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>to fall into</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>the hands of the liuing God.</hi> For becauſe hee ſaith in his anger, as it is written in the 32 Chapter of Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, <hi>I haue lifted my hand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward heauen, and ſaid, I am the euerliuing God; If I whet my glittering ſword, and mine ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d take hold on iudgement, I will execute vengance on myne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies, and will reward them that hate me.</hi> Praiſed be God which hath deliuered vs, and drawn vs from that burning furnace of hell by his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, who (as <hi>St</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the Galatians) <hi>was</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>reviled for our ſakes: and hath called vs out of perpetuall dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:27533:39"/> 
                  <hi>to his meruailous light.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. Is it poſſible for vs to bee ignorant what that torment is, and not knowe how much he hath ſuffered for to retaine vs in feare, and to make vs knowe the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the grace of God, &amp; the excellency of our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, who is alſo God eternally bleſſed?</p>
               <p>This whole precedent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe <note place="margin">How God fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth our deſignes.</note> hath led vs through all ages, and through all the moſt ordinarie conditions of humane life, yet in this voyage we haue knowne no thing but <hi>vanity and torment of Spirit.</hi> And it hath chiefly appeared, when we haue caſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:27533:40"/> our eies vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God; which doth from the higheſt heauens view all the actions of man, not as an idle ſpectator, but as a wiſe conductor and iuſt iudge. And there fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue he laughs at the deſignes of great men, and fruſtrateth their enterpriſes, deſtroyeth their tonges and ſpirits of Babylonian builders, ruineth their greatneſſe, &amp; breaketh their Scepters into ſhiuers; teaching man that hee is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but duſt, and his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome but meere blindneſſe; To the ende that hee may learne to contemne the worlde, and tranſport his hopes from earth to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:27533:40"/> and that hauing ſeene ſome beames of this terreſtriall ſplendor, which vaniſheth as lightning, he doth ſaie with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter. It is good that we bee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 9. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>here, let vs make our ſelues here Tabernacles.</hi> Happy is that man which hauing well knowne the vanity of this world doth retire himſelfe towards God: that he being in a ſure hauen a farre off, &amp; that being vnder his ſhadow as vnder a ſure couered place may contemplate the ruine of the vvicked, the inſtability of their deſignes, the folly of their hopes, &amp; the effects of the iudgement of God. Therevpon the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in the 92 Pſalme ſaith al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:27533:41"/> 
                  <hi>O Lord how glorious are thy workes, and thy thoughts are very deepe.! An vnwiſe man knoweth it not, and a foole doth not vnderſtand this. When the wicked grow as the graſſe, and all the workers of wickedneſſe doe floriſh, then they ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for euer.</hi> It behoueth vs here to note carefully that this Pſalme is entituled <hi>A ſong for the ſabbaoth day.</hi> For by it he doth advertiſe vs that this meditation requireth a quiet and reſting ſpirit which beeing reſtrained from the preſſe of humane actions doth range it ſelfe into the houſe of God, according to that vvhich hee ſaith in the 73 Pſalme, vvhere hee doth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:27533:41"/> confeſſe that the proſperity of vvicked men hath offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, and that hee could hardly digeſt it, vntil that hee had entred into the ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Almighty, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the end of ſuch men. For to vnderſtand vvhat the true happineſſe is, and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maske himſelfe to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginary felicity of this vvorld, it is not neceſſary to go to Philoſophical ſchools, or to builde his reſolutions vpon the opinion of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, but to enter into the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly houſe of God, and there learne vvhat the difference is betweene the riches, vvhich he ſcattereth vpon this great multitude, and that vvhich
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:27533:42"/> he reſerueth for his litle ons, vvhat the vncertainty of this vvorldly proſperity is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the certainty of Gods promiſes. But vvith what inſenſible chains doth Sathan lead men into perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? How doth he triumph ouer thoſe vvhich triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph in this vvorld? Hovve they that thinke themſelues moſt ſure are vpon the point of their ruine &amp; perpetual deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
               <p>Furthermore he doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <note place="margin">Of the vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of men</note> hovv vaine the glory of man is, in that ſome one doth boaſt of his particular ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth wherein it is vnpoſſible for him ever to equal a Bul: ſome other doe glorie in their beauty, when as it is onlie a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:27533:42"/> ſuperficial colour, which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth the bloud, bones, and braines, hiddeous thinges to ſee; Jt is alſo a thing that age &amp; many maladies haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to deforme. Some other doth glorie of his honour, and greatnes, when indeede he is poſſeſt in this ſtate with moſt trouble &amp; feare, &amp; leſſe liberty; beſides he is mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ſo high, that he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not fal but with breaking of his ovvne neck. Some other doth glory to be more dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; but if his belly be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in capacitie then other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it wil ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver exceed a barrel. <hi>This is alſo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſome conditions of men &amp; nations.</note> 
                  <hi>a vanity with a like peruerſity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe former thinges are
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:27533:43"/> generall; for vanities &amp; miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are common to all men, ſince that ſin hath ſubiected mankinde to them: But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there are ſome more then other, which are made examples of extreame miſerie. As poore beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, which are conſtrained through neceſſity to lie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bare pauement; as gallie ſlaues; and as thoſe miſerable wretches which are made mercenaries. The hundreth parte of humane kinde doth imperiouſly and impiouſlie torment the reſt; and thoſe that are feeble &amp; meane ſerue as prayes to the mightie. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the Turkes &amp; Pagans which poſſeſſe three parts of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:27533:43"/> the world, men are bought and ſold in the ſame faſhion, as horſes in a faire. For the buyer marketh their ſight, maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew their teeth, and feeleth the ſinewes of their Armes and legs. Great Princes keepe Millions of chained ſlaues for to labour in making of ſugar, in vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Mines, to ſerue in Gallies at ſea, &amp; to performe ſuch kinde of ſervility, that death is more tollerable to them then this kinde of life. There are certaine people vvhich haue for the ſpace of ſixe months continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all night, vvho liue in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes, and in the extremity of the extreameſt degree of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:27533:44"/> coldnes haue no heat to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them but only crueltie: Others there are on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, who liue among Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des continually ſcortched by the Sunne, a Country barren in fruites, &amp; fertill in Serpents, and Lyons. Our clymat in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſuch intemperature is as the garden of Nature, where God hath pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted moſt wealth and riches; but where he hath reaped leaſt fruite of graceful actions. And where theſe natural bleſſings are ſo ill husbandred, that amongſt all that aboundance there is nothing to be ſeene but mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and poverty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The vanity of the thoughts, deſires &amp; iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of men.</head>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:27533:44"/>
               <p> NOW that vve haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly and ſuperficiallie repreſented as vvith a Coale the vanity &amp; miſery of our nature, &amp; the actions of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let vs novve examine his thoughts. <hi>David</hi> in the 94. Pſalme ſaith, <hi>The Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the thoughts of man that they are vanity.</hi> For if anie <note place="margin">Idle &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable thoughts.</note> could but make a true colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his thoughts which haue only paſſed through his braine in one day: the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed multitude and varietie of them, being all very fooliſh, would aſtoniſh him: The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe fictions and ſtrange I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea's that painters conceipt in reſpect of theſe are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. For ſome man (when
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:27533:45"/> he hath ſetled himſelfe in his ſtudy, or ſome place where he thinketh to haue his ſpirit buſied about the moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous affaires) doth then begin to count the quarrees of his window, or, as the Emperor Domitian, to purſue little <note place="margin">Sueton.</note> flyes both with eie &amp; hand. Some one againe percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelfe deſtitute of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and being very penſiue, doeth adviſe with himſelfe what he would do if he were a King: or if that he had a milli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of crowns how he would ſpende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: or thinking of his owne domeſtique affaires, doth threed a chaine of tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hopes, &amp; by degrees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth very rich in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:27533:45"/> at the concluſion of which he fruſtrateth all that imagination, and returning to the conſideration of his preſent poverty, he modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Yea alſo du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of Sermons &amp; praier (when God ſpeaketh vnto vs, or wee to him;) our minds are abſtracted, &amp; thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſome other thing; Therefore if our beſt actions are infected with idle cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, how much more our vnprofitable howers, and ill ſpent time?</p>
               <p>Theſe frivolous thoughts mixed with vaine deſire, and a like ignorance do labor the minde, and giueth it no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: For man in his ſolitary
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:27533:46"/> thoughts doth ruminate the evils paſt; vexing himſelfe vvith the things preſent and fore-fearing things to come, yea thoſe things that ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver happen: he changeth his doubtfull feare into certaine miſeries: Many being miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble out of a feare that they ſhal be miſerable: &amp; many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of a feare that they ſhall die. Every day hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient affliction to torment vs. For who can ever bee in eaſe, if all the paſt and future evils doe render themſelues preſent to vs; the firſt by our memory; and the laſt by our feare? This naturall vnreſt is the cauſe that man loueth change; like vnto one that is
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:27533:46"/> ſicke, who deſireth continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to change his bed: yet notwithſtanding findes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pered in the laſt then in the firſt, thinking no repoſe to be but in weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. For he alwaies carryeth his griefe with him, &amp; findes little eaſe in cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging of ſides: yea (I dare ſay) if God had placed man betwixt good &amp; evill to take his choice of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and, as it were, to cut what hee thought good out of whole cloath, his blindnes is ſo great, that he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chuſe the worſt: or if he did make choice of the beſt, his perverſity is ſuch, that he would quickly convert it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ill. Jf God ſende ſuch no
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:27533:47"/> griefes, they will ſend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſome. Jf their owne griefes doe not trouble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the happineſſe of others wil torment them: and envy is more ſtinging then afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>From it alſo doth it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <note place="margin">Deſires.</note> that men deſire alwaies they knowe not what them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: they are greedy to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, but weake to put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as a bird that doth co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet to flie, but vſeth only one of her wings. Alſo men are diſtracted with contrary co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations: One complaineth that his wife is dead: Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſhee will not die. One mourneth for the loſſe of his children; another that hee hath ſome that bee very
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:27533:47"/> wicked. One diſturbed vvith buſines praiſeth domeſtique repoſe; and that opinion of <hi>Saul</hi> who did rather affect to liue obſcurely in the baſeſt poverty, then to bee exalted to the higheſt dignity: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being excluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique commande doth not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding breake his own necke to attaine it. Every thing doth ſeeme to vs beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, but that which wee haue, &amp; nothing delighteth vs but that which we cannot obtaine. Nothing doeth ſo much reioice vs as the hurte of another man: Jf ſome one decay in fortune wee ſmile, but it grieveth vs to ſee him receiue any honour.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:27533:48"/>
               <p> Jn this vanity of thoughts and vncertainety of deſires doth appeare a great weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſpirit. For our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſwaied more by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, and externall appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, then by the thing it ſelfe. Like vnto ſome ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors at a Tragedy, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that they know the Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be fabulous &amp; nothing concerning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: doe weepe out of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; when as they will not ſhed a teare for their owne vnfeined griefes. Some there be alſo that hang themſelues out of diſpaire, which the ſelfeſame houre would haue run away from the thruſt of a ſword, becauſe that this
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:27533:48"/> laſt kind of death commeth accompanied with horror and feare, vvhereas the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is ſo quickly diſpatched, that the ſight of it doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing amaze on. Opinions doe more gouerne vs then the things themſelues, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doe ſometimes eate meat vvhich they knowe not, and yet they finde it pleaſing to the taſt: but after, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome one hath told them what it is; their conceit vvill make them ſo ſicke at heart, that they vvill vomit it vp again. Some others haue more feare of a mouſe, or of a he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or of a Toad, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a ſword: certainly ſuch peeuiſh weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fantaſticall actions
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:27533:49"/> doe governe our imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Truely I knovv not hovv, but me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtudy to deceiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Some one will recite a tale for trueth, which hee knoweth to be moſt falſe; &amp; that ſo often, &amp; with ſo great an aſſurance that himſelfe in fine doth beleeue it. A huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band that knovveth his vvife to be deformed, notvvithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding becauſe ſhe is painted and diſguiſed, will begin to perſwade himſelfe that ſhee is faire: and ſhee her ſelfe will beleeue it, and thinke to bee reputed ſo: How many bee there which beleeue in a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe they vvil beleeue it? Which conteſt againſt
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:27533:49"/> their owne ſenſe? Which ſay among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is abſurd and not agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the Scripture; I will haue it thus, and will beleeue ſo. This is to haue a conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beliefe, not to haue his wil ſubiected to religion, but religion to his will.</p>
               <p>The infirmity of mans iudgement doth eſpecially ſhew it ſelfe in religion. For what hee thinketh touching the ſeruice of God doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeare by his exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior actions. In matters of newes wee doe ſooner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue one that hath ſeene it, then the common report: But in matters of religion it is contrary; for moſt doe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:27533:50"/> the vulgar opinion: which is as much as to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that which is moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, and then to hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe amongſt the multitude. If ſome one hath a deſire to put out mony, hee requireth for ſuch as are both faithfull and of ability, and will haue good aſſurance for it: But in matters of conſcience with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out farther enquiry hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth himſelfe and opinion to the Curate of the ſame place wherein he liueth. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue many other things which follow, that any may eaſily perceaue to bee moſt ridiculous: as to cloath with ſilke and gold the images of men, while that a poor beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:27533:50"/> goeth naked, which is the image of God: To put of the hat at the name of Jeſus, and not to remoue at the name of Chriſt. To weare a Croſſe hanging downe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the belly, while that the belly is a enimy to the croſſes of Chriſt. In going to a baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy houſe, or returning from ſome wicked fact, to ſay cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Pater noſters. To kneel down at the box which kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> vvhen it retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth empty from ſome ſicke body, as when it went full. To adore the <hi>Hoſt</hi> paſſing by in a little box, and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect it in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s body, which is come newly from receiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. To make their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:27533:51"/> with vvordes, and then preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to devour him with their teeth. To be inſolent &amp; deboſhed on day before le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and the next day following to be very graue &amp; ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. To employ their bleſſed beades for to obtaine remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their ſinnes. After the death of any great perſonag to cloath with blacke the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of our Lady, to the end that ſhe may participate of their griefes. To whip them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in publique for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent God, or to releaſe a ſoul out of Purgatory. In honour of the Saintes to burne can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles in the midſt of day. To conclude, man hath forged many ſtrange things in his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:27533:51"/> braine, &amp; would haue God to approue them. Nay hee is come to that paſſe, that hee doth aſſume to himſelfe the diſtribution of offices in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe; making one protector of a Country, another a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of ſome particular diſeaſe as if little Antes had power to diſpoſe of affaires belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Crown of France. <hi>this is alſo a vanity of vanities and an extreame imbecillity of Iudgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our ſelues which haue the true word of God for a rule to frame our actions by, are not exempted; &amp; our folly and vanity doth mixe it ſelfe with the ſole verity of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:27533:52"/> God. For in our ciuil actions if we haue need of counſaile, wee preſently addreſſe our ſelues to ſome friends: But in matters of Gods divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice we take counſaile of our minde and concupiſcences, which are our domeſticall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. Jf mony be due to vs from one, wee had rather al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaies haue the mony the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his promiſe; in celeſtiall matters it is contrary. For the <hi>Holie Goſpel is an obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> by which God hath promiſed vs ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hath ſealed it vvith the bloud of his Sonne; but we had rather keepe the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then receiue the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which is due at the daie of death, nay vve do endevor
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:27533:52"/> to prolong the date of it.</p>
               <p>Some doe recorde in the <note place="margin">Zonaras.</note> Emperour <hi>Honorious</hi> a great ſimplicity, &amp; childiſh weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that having a Henne nominated by him Rome, which hee did cheriſh, and ſo infinitely affect, that vvhen one came vnto him, ſaid that his Rome was loſt, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red very ſorrowfully, Alas! ſhe vvas here but even now. But the other replying ſaid, And pleaſe your Highneſſe I ſpeake not of a <hi>Henne,</hi> but of your city of Rome, which hath beene ſurpriſed and ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by <hi>Alaric Goth.</hi> The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror hearing this was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhat comforted, thinking that loſſe to be more tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:27533:53"/> Such is our ſimplicity we vvill not ſuffer one to touch our riches, but vvee will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure any to entice vs to vice, to ſeduce vs into error, &amp; to poyſon our ſoules. Jt is a great folly to refuſe a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine becauſe the Phyſitian is not eloquent. Why doe vve not then make account &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation of the preaching of the Goſpel, if the preacher be not eloquent, ſeeing that the holy Goſpell is the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine of our ſoules? Is it not then an extreame brutiſhnes for ſome vicious perſon to miſprize the Holy writ, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not adorned with flowers of Rhetorique? what is the reaſon then that the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:27533:53"/> worde of God doeth not pleaſe vs, If it bee not decked with flowers and compoſed vvith art, ſeeing that it is that ſacred vvorke &amp; doctrine of our reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with God? We do not receiue willingly the correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, if it be not very milde. <hi>This is alſo a vanity, diſtaſt, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Humour.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Falſe Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</note>
               </p>
               <p>Touching our iudgement vvhich we haue of others, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in eſteeming or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, it is moſt vaine &amp; ridiculouſly ignorant. For if there be a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, vve account him moſt ſtrong vvhich can carry the heavieſt; on the contrarie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout quarrels wee eſteeme
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:27533:54"/> him the moſt valiant which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beare nothing; attributing force and valour to weaknes and impatience. Jn matters of Ornament wee doe not iudge of the goodneſſe of a ſvvorde by the beauty of a ſcabbard: nor of the mettle of a horſe by the faireneſſe of the Bridle and Saddle: vvhy do we then meaſure our eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a man, either by his good or bad apparel? And if it be neceſſary that vve ſalute one for the ſtuffe of his cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes which he weareth, why doe wee not ſalute the ſame ſtuffe in the ſhops? Why do we iudge diſcreetly in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vaine and triuiall things, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as in a matter of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:27533:54"/> ſuch importance, as of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man we are moſt void of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? So ſome do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect a Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or Rent-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, becauſe he ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vp exactly his accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, vvhen he liueth in ſuch faſhion that he cannot giue an account to God. Some labour to till their Gardens and other grounds, and by it win much praiſe, vvhen as themſelues are barren and bring foorth <note place="margin">vaine feare.</note> no fruit of good workes.</p>
               <p>We are as much vaine &amp; childiſh in our feares as in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thing. For as little Infants doe play vvith fire, &amp; burne themſelues, but feare vvhen they ſee their father comming (masked with a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:27533:55"/> frowning countenance) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards them: So men deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to dally vvith pleaſures becauſe of their luſtre, at the length looſe themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they fear God their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder the maske of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or death. Alſo ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth inge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in himſelfe either fooliſh or pernicious feares. Some one beeing iealous, that his wife doth affect others, ende voreth to eſpy &amp; ſearch out that vvhich hee feareth to find: &amp; by this meanes ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her, ſo that ſhe ſeeketh to be reve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged in ſuch nature which he formerly ſuſpected. Some other fearing to liue
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:27533:55"/> without honor, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mits ſuch things that ſubiects his body to ſome cruell torment, and ſtaineth the memory of him with perpetuall infamy. So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e other feareth the want of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but he ſhal wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it, &amp; die without it. Some againe fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth he ſhal dy before marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; but God wil attend that time, and by wedlocke will make him twice; miſerable.</p>
               <p>When I conſider what <note place="margin">Childiſh wiſdome.</note> humane wiſedome is, I finde it agreeable to the Induſtry of Moles, which dig vnder ground with much dexterity but are blind when they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e into the Sunne. So wee haue much skill in earthly affaires, to ſell, to couenant, and to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:27533:56"/> ſupplant any one; But take one of theſe men which is moſt ſubtill in theſe things, and bring him to the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and light of the holy Goſpell, and there hee is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together blind, and of a ſelfe conceit will continue ſo. For during the time that he doth foreſee future eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of eſtate, hee is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of his own deſtruction: while that he diſcourſeth on the affaires of kingdomes hee is a ſlaue to the Deuill. And notwithſtanding that blind iudgement of his dares conteſt againſt the euer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God; the folly and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes againſt the diuine wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:27533:56"/> of the Father of light; And the diſcretion of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the prouidence of the Almighty. For the wicked do couer themſelues with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, craft and diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: like vnto little childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which thinke that they are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently hidden when their eies are cloſed: beleeuing that no body ſeeth them, when they ſee no body. But in the mean time God perceiues them both naked &amp; vncouered, yea better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For God is not only al hand in holding and condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the whole vniverſe, but alſo all eie in ſeeing &amp; dicerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all things in it. The thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt bodies are to him tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:27533:57"/> and darknes it ſelfe is to him light, &amp; therfore the Prophet <hi>David</hi> doeth iuſtlie reprehend that fooliſh wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the 94. Pſalme, where he ſaith <hi>Vnderſtand yee vnwiſe among the people: and yee fooles, when will yee be wiſe? He that planted the eare, ſhal he not heare? Or hee that formed the eie, ſhall he not ſee?</hi> Novve in this place he calleth them vnwiſe, not which are fooles and runne vp and downe the ſtreetes: nor thoſe priuate &amp; particular men which are vvithout office: nor the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy-ſpirited Commons, but ſuch as are crafty, &amp; manage affaires with dexterity, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by their ſagacity to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:27533:57"/> themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God; or to dazell the Eies of his ſacred proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Like vnto the moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Agues, which are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the appearance of cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: ſo the moſt ridiculous folly is that which lyeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the appearance of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>It behoueth alſo the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to exerciſe his meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to bee Spectator of the actions and thoughts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of al the vnprofitable la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of his life. For it is in humane life, as in a Faire, where there commeth tvvo ſorts of people; one for to buy &amp; ſell; the other only to ſee. Man that feareth God is
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:27533:58"/> like to one of thoſe which come to ſee, he is not here to be Idle, &amp; ſearch for nothing but to conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plate the works of God &amp; humane actions: but he may ſay (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath ſeene al the delights that rhe curious vanity of men can ſhewe forth) O how many things are there in this world which I haue nothing to do withall? What if during this contemplation ſome one do ioſſell or throng vpon him, or if one cut his purſe, that is doe afflict or depriue him of any thing, all that ſuch a one vvill do is, to goe out of that company, &amp; knowing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee a ſtranger in this world will trauell towardes
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:27533:58"/> his Country, where that ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall habitation is, preſſing alwaies (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>towards the marke for the price</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3 14.</note> 
                  <hi>of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> If the vvorld co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne him, he will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne that contempt, as knowing himſelfe better then the world, and to bee called to a better hope: he vvill eſteeme the promiſes allurements of the vvorlde, vaine, the occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations of men baſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunat. And according to the example of <hi>Mary</hi> in the tenth of <hi>Luke, Hee will chuſe the good part, which ſhal not bee taken from him:</hi> Concluding all his Meditations after the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner as <hi>Salomon</hi> doth
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:27533:59"/> in the ende of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes: The ende of all, is the feare of God, and the keeping of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: for in it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſumme of mans being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now therefore after all this Meditation let vs reſt our ſelues vpon theſe two Maximes and propoſitions, which are the true foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that zeale is grounded vpon. The firſt is for to loue God, it behoueth to conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the world. The ſecond is, that for to contemne the worlde it is neceſſary for the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to know his own worth, nobleneſſe, and excellency of his vocation.</p>
               <p>The firſt Maxime is taken out of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> in his firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:27533:59"/> 
                  <hi>Loue not the world, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 2. ver. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>the things that are in the world. If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue the world, the loue of the Father is not in him. For all that is in the world (as the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eies, and the pride of the life) is not of the Father, but is of the world. And the worlde paſſeth away, and the luſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: but hee that fulfilleth the will of God abideth for euer.</hi> Nothing doth ſo farre ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vs from the loue of God as our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the world, ſeeing that the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for to admoniſh vs doth call the <hi>world the kingdome of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 16. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the Divell.</hi> But as the Moone hath no light vnleſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sunne: So our ſoules haue
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:27533:60"/> not any light but by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our God; and by a conſequent neither more nor leſſe: but euen as the Moone doth looſe her light whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe is hid within the ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dow of the earth: So alſo do our ſouls looſe their bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; for they are called in the holy Scripture <hi>the Infantes of light,</hi> when they moleſt and wrap themſelues within the ſhaddow of earthly things, cares, and worldly concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences: which wee ought to tread vnder our feete accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the example of the Church, vvhich as it is vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the 12. of the <hi>Apocalyps hath vnder her feet the Moone,</hi> that is, the mutable inſtabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:27533:60"/> of theſe inferiour thinges. To this purpoſe alſo Jeſus Chriſt vvould that <hi>The peny ſhould be reſtored to Caeſar,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that it had his Jmage on it. Let vs therefore then giue our ſelues to God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wee beare his ovvne Image. But the Jnconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is that we do often abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Image in rubbing it againſt the Earth, and pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſoules with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoughts and deſires.</p>
               <p>That wee may therefore miſpriſe the earth, &amp; all that the word doth promiſe, it requireth that wee come to the ſecond point, which is, to know perfectly vvhat the vvorth and excellency of the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:27533:61"/> faithful is. For vvhen as men by an vnfriendly amity, and cruell welwilling do ſollicite ſome one to doe ill, which hath the feare of God, and to offende his conſcience in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending God, Jt behoueth the faithful to thinke in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: vvhat? I that am a childe of God, and am of a celeſtiall noblenes, that am one of the firſt borne whoſe names are regiſtred in heauen, ſhall I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme <note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> the promiſes of the world, which when they are moſt certaine, they are too baſe for me to meditate on? to delude the ſon of a Prince with an apple? To entice vvith ſiluer the Sonne of the King of Heauen, to offende
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:27533:61"/> his Father? And after the enſample of <hi>Eſau</hi> to ſell my birth-right for a meſſe of pottage? Such perſuaſions ſhall not by any meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe me. God will not afflict me with ſo great a blindnes. We are vnworthy to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt, if wee doe not eſteeme our ſelues to be better then the world. Was it not for the loue of the faithfull that the world was framed? Will not God rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate it againe for to reedify for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a fairer houſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, vvhere ſhall bee the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of glory? For this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or climate is inferior to the vvorth &amp; dignity of the children of God. You that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:27533:62"/> feare God &amp; truſt in his Son, knowe that it is you that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derprop the world, and that nouriſh the wicked in it. Therefore the enimies of God are bound in obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you. For he doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerue the worlde out of a reſpect, vvhich he hath towards his choſen and elect, vvhereof ſome are mixed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the euill, and others are yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne. It is vvritten in the 6. of the Apocalyps, <hi>That God doth attend vntill our fellowe ſeruants be accompliſhed.</hi> And therefore this is one of the reaſons why <hi>that Chriſt doth call the faithfull the fault of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 13</note> 
                  <hi>earth,</hi> vvhich is as much as a little part amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:27533:62"/> conſerueth the reſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layeth their deſtruction. For God conſerueth the ſinfull becauſe of the good, to the end that they ſhould ſerue as medicines to them, and that the might and power of our aduerſaries might ſerue to compell vs to the feare of God and to truſt in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. Such being the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Gods elect aboue the reſt, it behoueth vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the pleaſures, riches, &amp; greatneſſe of the vvorlde, as things that are moſt ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and as the painted king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes vvhich the Deuill ſhewed vnto Chriſt. Like thoſe vvhich from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the Alpes doe
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:27533:63"/> looke into <hi>Campania,</hi> vvhere the greateſt Citties ſeeme like vnto little Cottages: how much leſſe and baſe wil they ſeeme then if they were diſcerned from heauen? Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence therfore it behoueth that the faithful contemplat humane things, and that hee tranſport inſtantly his heart to heauen, ſince that there is his treaſure. And conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the Pallaces of Princes, hee will eſteeme them as habitations of Ants; &amp; the turbulent murmuring of men as the buzzing of an angry ſwarme of Bees; and contemplating from thence vvhat things are moſt greate and apparant in the earth, he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:27533:63"/> vvill ſay, <hi>The vanity of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that all is vanity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Holy glory wil not hinder Chriſtian humility. For wee knowing the vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe in our ſelues, doe finde our dignity in Ieſus Chriſt. If repentance doth humble vs, faith doth exalt vs: If we are nothing before God vvee are ſomewhat in God, &amp; in his fatherly affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And therefore in this the faithfull are contrary to vvorldly men. For they do lift their eies to heauen by too much pride, but preſſe downe their heart on the earth vvith avarice and inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency: vvhereas the godly on the contrary hath his eies
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:27533:64"/> vpon the earth by humility, as the Publican which durſt not lift his eies to heauen, but hath his heart in heauen by faith and hope. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of this vvorlde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes not out of a loue to himſelfe; but out of a true af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The wickedneſſe which now reigneth.</head>
               <p>MOreouer the contempt of the vvorld borne of the loue of God ſhal at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth grow to hatred of the world, when that beſides the vanity and miſery of it, he ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the miſchiefe and enmity againſt the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which there reigneth;
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:27533:64"/> when beſides that vanity which ſome doe lay open to the view of all, he wil repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to himſelfe the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are cloſely kept, &amp; the treaſons, adulteries, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which are priuatly and lurkingly committed; when he ſhall conſider the vials of Gods wrath and diſpleaſure powred generally vpon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane kinde. For in the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this vvorld, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth vs to leaue out no part of it, but to obſerue all manner of Nations &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, amongſt which there are many Pagans, which not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a Conſequent, but alſo by expreſſe profeſſion adore the Deuill. The Eaſt Indies
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:27533:65"/> dedicate their Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples to him, and honour him with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. The Weſt Indies are afflicted and tormented or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily with euil Spirits. In moſt part of the North lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king deceipts, and aſſuming ſtrange ſhapes are very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt the Inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: Sorcery is there an ordinary profeſſion; &amp; the Divel raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth without contradiction. Jn that Country, which did once flouriſh, where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles had planted ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Holy Goſpell,</hi> the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are nowe changed into <hi>Moſquees,</hi> and Temples of Idolatry; In the Weſt the head of the viſible Church is become an earthly <hi>Monarck:</hi>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:27533:65"/> &amp; banks are erected in thoſe places where in time paſt was the houſe of God. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe erroneous and envious people are ſcattere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which blaſpheme againſt Ieſus Chriſt, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving perſecuted him in his life do iniuriouſly wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him after his death. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try from whence come de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and orders for Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath in it publique brothell houſes, and Sodomy is there an vſuall cuſtome: Here it is alſo where doubts in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that concerne a mans faith are decided in the midſt of corruption.</p>
               <p>There only remaineth in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:27533:66"/> the world a handfull of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which ſerue Jeſus Chriſt in truth and verity, and they can ſcarce receiue breath in this aire which is ſo contrary to them, being here as fiſhes without water, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of great Maſſacres, as pieces of boards ſcattered after the breaking of a great veſſel: And yet neuertheleſſe amongſt theſe few (which are ſubſtracted out of the reſt of the world,) Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth encreaſe, as a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre or vlcer. Quarrels, vanity, ſuperfluity in apparell, Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, ambition, ſumptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which ſpendeth fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, doeth infect the one part of this ſmal troupe. For God
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:27533:66"/> is il ſerued in priuat families, their almes are colde; they pray ſeldome; &amp; read never: In briefe a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagion of vices, by converſing with our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, doeth infect vs, vvhich is the firſt ſtep to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: For error creepes in to vs by vice, and ſpirituall fornication by corporall. Jf therfore where God is moſt purely knowne, he be there il ſerued: Hovv much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the reſt of the world? If vices do harbor within the Sanctuary, hovv much more in the body of the Church, and habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wicked? Therefore Chriſt doth right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly call Sathan the Prince of the world, &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> doth iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:27533:67"/> vvrite in the 2. of the <hi>Actes Saue your ſelues from that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe generation.</hi> For Sathan lyeth in ambuſh for vs all; this age is infectious: vices are like vnto glue; temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtrong: our enimies mightie: our ſelues feeble &amp; ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: &amp; the vvay of Saluation nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and full of thornes: <hi>and few there be</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that finde it.</hi> And thoſe which finde it, do not alwaies keepe it: but many, hauing knowne the truth, do leaue it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to their vomit. Let vs know then a place ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that we may paſſe by as ſtrangers, which do not only paſſe but alſo run from it, fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the world, to come
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:27533:67"/> vnto God. For we ſhal neuer haue repoſe vnleſſe wee reſt our ſelues vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen moueth alwaies, and yet it is the place of our reſt: on the contrary the Earth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth alwaies, and yet it is the place of our motion. The <hi>Quadrantes</hi> &amp; <hi>Horologies</hi> imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the motion of Heauen: but the faith of the beleeuers doeth imitate the reſt which is aboue all. <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> did more eſteeme the ſmoake of his owne houſe, then the flame of an others; Howe much more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would he eſteeme the flame of his owne chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney than the ſmoake of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? We are here ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:27533:68"/> this is not our houſe, our ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation is in heauen. Let vs compare the ſmoake of this ſtrange houſe, and the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Earth with the beauty and ſplendor of our ovvne dvvelling, vvhich is in the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Here is the raigne of Sathan; there the kingdome of God. Here is a valley of teares; there the height of mirth. Here wee ſovv in ſorrovve; there vvee reape in Ioy; Here we ſee the light of the Sunne through tvvo little holes, vvhich are called the eies: there vvee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue light from God on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſide, as if vve vvere all Eyes.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:27533:68"/>
               <p> Therefore becauſe God is all in all. To him be honor and glory in this vvorld, and in the world to come. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
